Stanford
University Okay so we've talked about a
lot of things so far fields quanta of
fields the relationship between fields
and particles that's the relationship
between fields and their Quant what are
the Quant the Quant are the discrete
indivisible units of energy that quantum
mechanics uh
implies for
waves for waves and waves of course are
Fields fields and waves are more or less
the same thing we've discussed the
properties the all not the properties of
individual particles very much but we've
discussed some general properties the
properties of having uh energy momentum
the properties of having Spin and the
property of either being a firon or a
boson every particle is either a firon
or a
boson fion are the partic parles that
don't like to live together in the same
state bons are the particles that do
like to congregate and do condense into
the same state we've talked about wave
equations on occasion or the field
equations if you like more generally
various for kinds of field equations and
we talked about how field equations can
be generated from lonians from action
principles the quantum mechanical
version of the lran is is a kind of tool
for codifying or codifying whatever the
right word is codifying the interactions
between particles various terms in the
lran things like for example products of
fields represent
processes which um we can call vertices
where particles come in and other
particles go out that would for example
be a term in the lran which would have
four powers of a field in it so we've
talked about these General
things uh we haven't talked very much
about specific particles tonight well I
expected to spend the first half hour uh
beating around the bush bush a little
bit looks like we're going to spend a
few more minutes beating around the bush
but then I want to come to really
writing down what the particles are you
know who are the players in the
drama and uh start going through them
more or less well not quite one by one
but in groups and trying to give them
some personality give them some um names
some properties and also what it is they
do and how they uh how they come into uh
into physics into ordinary physics okay
but before I do that there's kind of a
triangle of
Concepts that we've discussed two legs
of but not the third leg very much the
triangle is
particles or field Quant
particles
fields and in modern physics pretty much
for every elementary particle now we're
going to have to think very hard in the
future not tonight what is an elementary
particle and what is a composite
particle we will come back to that and
you might think I mean everybody here
probably has some answer if I were to
ask you how do you distinguish a
composite particle from an elementary
particle and you will always be
frustrated you will always find some
slippery reason that your definition
didn't work but for the moment let's
nevertheless imagine that there are
Elementary particles and that the
elementary particles are the quanta of
Elementary Fields fundamental fields in
the in the
theory uh and so there more or less in
one to one correspondence but there's a
third leg to this triangle anybody know
what it
is of course you don't know what I'm
thinking so even if you didn't know what
it was you still wouldn't know
it forces forces forces and in a certain
sense
forces Force forces okay basically for
every field there is a
particle for every field there is a
force electric field gives rise to
electric forces gravitational field give
rise to gravitational forces it may be
less obvious to you uh what the um what
the electron field electron Has a
Field uh it also gives rise to forces
and we'll talk about them a little bit
so there's kind of a a correspondence
that goes this way there's a
correspondence which goes this way there
must also be a correspondence which goes
this way
a way of thinking about forces which is
not based on fields but which based on
particles if this correspondence or this
Triangle really makes sense so I want to
talk about that a little bit I know many
of you know the idea but let's just
discuss it for a
moment uh let me first discuss it in the
context of
electrodynamics how forces come out of
think now this is classical
electrodynamics for the moment the
complete Field view of
things supposing I
put two
charges into space and I want to know
the force between them how do I
calculate it well you could know the you
could know the rule that the force is
equal to the product of the charges
times times 1 / R 2 and so forth or you
could try to calculate it a different
way you could try to say what does the
what do these two charges do to space
what they do to space is they create
electric Fields right they essentially
that's the thing they do they create an
electric field that fills
space and I don't want to write down the
details of what that electric field is
but let's just say this is the electric
field let's forget the second particle
and just write down the electric field
due to the first particle whatever it is
the electric field due to the first
particle incidentally it's proportional
to the electric charge of the the first
particle so let's explicitly put that in
E of the first
particle times the electric
field uh divided by the electric charge
this electric field here I've divided
out the electric charge maybe I
shouldn't call it e let's call it e
without the factor of the electric
charge in it and put a little hat over
it right that's this electric charge and
what is the field energy anybody know
what the formula for the field energy is
in an electric field electric Fields
have energy they store their energy as a
distribution of energy in
space and the field energy the the
density of field energy is the square of
the electric field right so we Square
this and we integrate it over all space
the volume and that's the energy stored
in this in the electric field of the
particle now this energy does not depend
on where we put the particle right the
field will move if we move the particle
the field will move with it but the
field energy will always be the
same right the electric field will
adjust to the position of the charge the
field will always give rise to exactly
the same field energy and this field
energy here remember eal
mc^2 that field energy is part of the
mass of the
particle it contributes the field
contributes to the energy of the
particle and therefore it contributes to
the mass of the particle there's another
way of thinking about a bit of
renormalization that there's some extra
mass there because the field surrounds
the particle in this way okay I don't
want to belabor that now what about the
second particle supposing the first
particle wasn't there but the second
particle was there this of course is the
energ
e not the electric
field this is the
energy if there was only particle two
the field energy would
be the integral of E2
times the electric
field of the second particle squared now
if the two particles are not at the the
same place well let's not worry about
the part this this one would also be
independent of the position of this
particle here what about the energy if I
have both
particles if I have both particles then
I have to add up the field first before
squaring it so the electric field if I
have two
particles will be the sum of the two
electric fields electric field not the
not energy let's call this energy
n h well let's not call it h energy just
n um the
energy first of all the electric field
the electric field will be the sum of
the two electric
Fields the electric field will be e
E1 plus E1 E1 plus E2 E2
where these are the electric fields of
particle one and particle 2 this will be
the total electric field incidentally
the electric fields are vectors and so
we might put little Vector signs above
them the field energy you get by
squaring this whole thing so the field
energy is the integral over space there
are three terms the first term is E1 2
E12 gotten by by squaring this the
second term is plus E2
e22 and the third term is the
interesting
one it's the product of E1 E2 twice as a
matter of fact times
e1.
E2 actually dotproduct all right what is
this first term
here it's the self energy of one
particle by itself it doesn't depend on
the position of the particle it's just a
number it's part of the mass of the
particle let's forget it it's already
there as part of the mass of the
particle what about this
one also part of the self energy of the
second
particle what about this one here this
one is not the energy of either particle
separately it's to the product of the
charges and it's proportional to the
product of the fields what if the
particles were infinitely far away so
far away that their Kum Fields hardly
overlapped at all you take one particle
so far away that uh the Kum fields are
hardly overlapping then this is going to
be zero because wherever E1 is not zero
E2 will be zero or almost zero wherever
E2 is non zero E1 will be close to zero
so this will be very very small as you
take the particles apart but what about
when you bring them together when you
bring them together the product of E1 *
E2 will not be
small nearby where the particles are
both Fields will be appreciable and you
will get a contribution from
this what is that contribution that
contribution as a function of distance
well first of all it's proportional to
the product of the charges
it depends on the distance and of course
if you work it out as you might expect
it's nothing but the kulum Force One r s
but I like to say it this way because it
gives you the following picture that
putting in both charges taking them far
apart they don't
affect well they're just they're simply
just independent objects as you bring
them together they deform and distort
the field in a way that depends on the
distance between them and the
distortions of the field in between them
that field energy that field energy
which is the contribution because both
of them are there that's the force law
so that's a purely field point of view
of
forces a purely field point of view of
forces but if fields are nothing but
collections of Quant and quanta are
particles there must also be a way to
think about forces in terms of particles
so let's let's talk about that a little
bit before discussing electrodynamics in
this way let's talk about a slightly
different setup a completely well
actually a very completely different
setup let's talk about molecular
forces what do molecular forces come
from I'll give you one source of there
are several there are several origins of
molecular forces but here's a setup I
want to think
about uh
let's begin with a pair of protons and a
single
electron what is this a proton over
here a proton over
here and a single
electron if this proton were very far
away then the ground state of the
electron in the presence of the proton
would just be the hydrogen atom ground
state it would be governed by some sort
of shring a wave function let's draw the
shring a wave function the ground state
would be the ground state of the
hydrogen
atom and in the ground state if this
proton weren't there at all not there at
all the electron in its ground state
would certainly be found in the position
nearby this
proton now what if there are two protons
over here one proton over here another
proton over here pretty far away but not
infinitely far away then then there is
another possible state of the electron
with exactly the same energy where the
electron is not over here but it's over
here with the corresponding wave
function pushed over to here it has
exactly the same energy why because the
two protons are of the same
kind uh and everything is completely
symmetric over here so if the electron
is in Orbit well a quantum mechanical
orbit around this proton or if it's in
quantum mechanical orbit around this
proton the ground state energy will be
exactly the same as if there was only
one
proton but it's not quite
true why isn't it exactly true well if
the protons are not infinitely far away
there are processes that could happen
which could not happen if they were
infinitely far
away anybody know what the process is
that can happen to the electron if the
two uh tunneling effect which I guess
the tunneling tunneling effect yeah the
tunneling effect the electron placed
over here into its ground
state can with a small probability
suddenly appear in this atom over here
that's called quantum mechanical
tunneling uh it has to overcome an
energy barrier in between in between the
two it takes some energy to pull the
electron out of this atom it'll get get
that energy back when it drops into this
atom but it has to go over this hill can
it go over the hill classically it can't
but Quantum mechanically it can tunnel
from one place to
another don't stand there and try to
watch the tunneling what happens if you
try to watch for the electron going back
and forth like anything else in quantum
mechanics watching it ruins
it uh you can watch over here you can
say well you can stand over here and
wait for the electron to appear over
here but if you watch it from in here
you'll ruin the phenomenon so the
electron can hop back and forth hop back
and forth simply means that there's a
tunneling transition a tunneling rate or
a tunneling probability that if you put
it over here it can appear over here if
it appears over here and you wait a
while it'll reappear over here and so
forth okay this process sets up a kind
of equilibrium longterm equilibrium in
which the electron has a equal
probability of being over here and over
here with a wave function looks which
looks like the sum of the two wave
functions well the sum divided by the
square root of two in order for
probability to to add up to one all
right so it looks like the sum of the
two wave functions which I didn't draw
very
well but in the middle over
here it's slightly different you might
you might draw the exact wave function
of the
electron orbiting particle one as if
particle two were not
there same thing for particle
two and then addir them up well the
correct tunneling wave function the
correct equilibrium wave function is not
exactly the sum of these two wave
functions it's a little bit different in
here a little bit not much but the point
is the
energy of the system is not exactly what
it would be if the two protons were
infinitely far away from each other if
they were infinitely far away from each
other you could put the proton the
electron over here it would have a
certain energy or over here and it would
have exactly the same energy
when you put them closer together the
energy of the electron is not exactly
the same as it would be if
the uh if they were far apart if they
were infinitely far apart so if I would
to plot the
energy if I were to plot the energy as a
function of the distance between them
when they're very very far apart the
energy of that electron is simply the
energy of the electron with only one
proton and the other one just not there
at all at large distances the energy
would just be whatever it was but as you
bring the protons together the energy of
that two protons plus electron is a
little bit less turns out to be a little
bit less and that little bit less
uh is a function of the distance between
them so now we have a situation when the
system is in equilibrium with the
electron tunneling back and forth and in
equilibrium between the two the energy
is a function of the distance between
them what's the relationship between
force and
energy you can think of this as
potential energy you can think of this
as a potential energy between the two
protons
ener the derivative of the energy so the
derivative of the
energy the energy has a gradient in here
Force always P pushes you toward
decreased energy and so this effectively
creates an attraction between the two
protons that
attraction is a kind of Cove valent Bond
it's a kind of um force between the two
of them which is due du to the sharing
of an electron or to the fact that the
electron can be in a superposition of
quantum states in the two wells in the
two uh uh potentials of these two things
here now does that mean that a proton
and another proton with an electron
between them which has this attractive
force will bind together not quite
because there's another Force around
what's the other Force
around electrostatic force the system
doesn't have zero charge altogether and
so there's a repulsion force and the
repulsion force can overwhelm the
attraction Force but nevertheless there
is a force between two protons if there
is an electron around which is due in a
sense to the jumping back and forth of
the electron or to the diminishing of
the energy by the wave function sort of
adjusting a little bit a little bit
better than it would if you just added
the two wave functions
together um as I said that's the origin
of calent bonds sharing uh sharing of
electrons and in this case you can think
of it you can draw a picture now the
picture may or may not uh do anything
for you you have a proton over here
that's the world line of a proton
another world line of the proton and the
electron might start out being bound to
this proton hop across to this proton
hop back across to this proton you
shouldn't take this too literally
because if you stood in the middle as I
said you would disrupt the process but
it's a description of the quantum
mechanical state of the electron in
between the two protons what it does
this possibility of the electron jumping
back and forth lowers the energy
relative to if you just had one proton
and just one electron in the bound State
there that means that there is an
effective force and you know you can
picture it this is this picture is um a
very is like any analogy it's often very
very
misleading uh but uh the presence of the
electron in between the two protons
creates an attractive Force it's called
particle
exchange it's called particle exchange
or electron exchange between the two uh
between the two protons now yeah could
you think of it as being the electrons
hopping back and forth is reducing the
effective positive charge of the no I
don't think that that is quite the right
picture it doesn't really depend on the
electric charges um it just depends on
the fact that you can find by adding
together two wave functions you can find
a wave function with a little bit lower
energy than either one separately is
this whatman referred to as like lik
like as what lman used to say like lik
like
light likes light I don't know no no no
no he was probably talking about the
Boza statistics of the that photons like
to uh like to be in the same state I I
don't know what he was talking about he
made the statement that he said that
like likes like like electrons like each
other photons no no electrons hate each
other they don't like to be in the same
state photons like each other they love
to be in the same state I think he was
probably talking about uh the uh the
opposite of the exclus usion principle
for photons the bza statistics of them
course I don't know protons have a tendy
to repel
protons that's because of their electric
charge right now what happens is when
you put the electron between them is
that reducing the repulsive it does a
little
bit but uh not uh not very much and in
fact the uh the force due to the
electron jumping back and forth is a
much shorter range Force than the
electrostatic attraction so this force
would only be important at relatively
small distances whereas the kolom force
would fall off much more slowly so the
kolom force would be a longer range
force uh but you know it is there it is
there the places where it shows up is if
you have a neutral system I mean it
shows up better if you have a neutral
system if you have two
electrons so that the total charge of
the system is zero
then of course you'll have the
possibility one electron orbiting around
this proton a second electron orbiting
around this proton
here now the two objects here they're
called atoms hydrogen atoms they're
neutral there is no electrostatic force
between them but you still have this
possibility of electrons jumping
across right electrons can jump across
or tunnel across and then it does create
an attractive Force which can bind uh
bind an atom bind a um
molecule but but even so unless I'm
mistaken H2 plus positively charged
hydrogen is bound yeah yeah yeah it is
bound but it does overcome yeah at small
distances at small distances it is
enough to overcome the Kum Force that's
right yeah is there any possibility
between the two protons it's creating
some kind of attention between that
creates some third force that the
electron kind of oring around well it
doesn't create a third Force but it
creates a sort of slightly nonlinear
effect due to the sub due to the two
forces but uh it's just a solution of
the Schrodinger equation in the presence
of the two forces does not have the
energy that it would have if it was just
one of those charges there but uh let's
let's uh let's let's leave it at that
there is this notion of the energy being
lowered by the possibility of uh of
alternating between two Quantum States
is is this thing all related to
Quantum um not so much quantum
entanglement it's
um it's related to what are called off
diagonal elements in the hamiltonian but
uh which is it's not too closely related
to entanglement I would say um for
entanglement normally you need two
electrons you only need one electron for
this for hot very hot very very high
temperatures does the
electron uh electron move between the
protons much higher probility well at
high temperatures at high temperatures
of course it depends on the temperature
at very very high temperatures all it'll
happen is the electron will get kicked
out and you know go to uh Alpha Cent
and it won't even remember the fact that
there was a proton around if it gets hit
hard enough by a very hot
Photon um but if the if the temperature
is not that extreme what it can do is
cause even if you only had a single atom
it could cause the electron to occupy
higher levels now higher levels have
bigger wave functions so the overlap
between the higher wave functions could
be larger and it would certainly have
some effect on the force
uh but uh that's a uh kind of special
effect all right we have we have a
concept uh that we see in the classical
electrodynamics that the effect of
having two
charges changes the energy in between
relative to what it would have been if
you only had one and it creates a force
similar kind of thing here if you have
two force centers and the possibility of
the of the uh elect
being in a superposition of states in
other words of the um of the equilibrium
being in a Quantum
superos of the two states the two states
being over here or over here that also
lowers the energy and creates a
force
um is there a way to think about the
kulum force here in quantum mechanics
where it is in some sense similar to
this jumping back and forth of the
electron yeah there is
um let's come back to a single proton a
single proton is interacting with the
electromagnetic field that means it's
interacting with the field whose quanta
are
photons classically we might just
describe it by solving the field
equations for the electric field in the
presence of a Charged particle Quantum
mechanically we think about it
differently particularly in Quantum
field Theory we think about it as the
emission and absorption of
photons all right that's what the lran
of Quant of electrodynamics tells us it
tells us about the probability for the
emitting and
absorbing absorption of
photons so one way of thinking about the
electron is that the actual physical
electron is a quantum mechanical
superposition of States in which first
of all there are no
photons a superposition of a state with
no photons a superposition of states in
which a photon has been emitted and
therefore there's a a photon present so
it's a Charged particle together with a
photon
around two photons can be emitted the pH
can be reabsorbed the net effect in the
end is some kind of
equilibrium distribution qu quantum
mechanical equilibrium distribution of
photons surrounding the electron and you
can measure those photons I mean a
little bit different than measuring free
photons these photons are sort of
trapped at the electron they're emitted
and
reabsorbed and if I have another
electron over here it is also emitting
and absorbing photons so there's an
equilibrium okay but every so
often now this should be thought of in
the language of findan diagrams every so
often a photon which is emitted from
here gets absorbed over
here right I always think about it as a
two jugglers each juggling balls and
every so often if they happen to be
close enough together a mistake will be
made and Joe will grab Mo's uh juggling
uh
objects okay really what you really want
to do is you really want to calculate
the energy due to the electromagnetic
field or due to the quantum
superposition of photons that are
present you want to calculate that
energy as a function of the distance
between
the charge
particles when they're very far
apart the two energies just add you just
get the sum of the energy of one charged
particle and another charged particle
but as they get closer together the
charges begin to influence each other or
in the language of Fineman diagrams the
emission of one Photon by one particle
and the absorption of that same Photon
by another particle creates a force
creates an energy which is not exactly
the sum of the two energies and that
energy is the kolum force between the uh
between the charg particles so we have
two distinct languages well apart from
just the writing down the kulum force
law we have two other ways of thinking
about forces one of them is through
classical field Theory where you
calculate the fields of objects and
square them and the other way is through
the exchange of particles find Min
diagrams where particles are exchanged
back and forth any particle can be
exchanged in some context or another so
every kind of particle in one way or
another produces a force in molecular
physics it's the exchange of electrons
which create
forces um in electrodynamics it's the
exchange of photons back and forth which
create
forces so any particle
any particle is also connected with a
force when that particle can be
exchanged or jump back and forth between
two something else we'll we'll describe
some more
examples but um I did want before we
move on to just discuss the relationship
between particles and forces so we more
or less have a one to1 to1
correspondence
particles fields for which those those
particles are the
quanta and forces which are associated
with exchange processes where that
particular kind of particle can bounce
or jump back and forth that's a that's
an important theme so when people say
that there are four forces in nature no
there's a force for every possible kind
of
particle
uh and um we will discuss some of them
as we go along okay I think it's comes
it's time now to start naming the
particles listing them listing their
properties and discussing what they can
do what kind of processes they can
engage in
and I could write down a big long list
of all the elementary particles and then
give you a test next week to see whether
you memorized it or not um that wouldn't
be fun at
all I think it's probably better to
divide them up into small
groups groups which are in some way
simply related to each other get
familiar with them a little bit and what
they can do before we try to write down
the whole damn standard model of
particle physics which is a monstrosity
I mean you know it's it's not my fault
certainly not my fault that the standard
model of elementary particle physics is
an ugly monstrous mess it's not Steve
weinberg's fault it's nobody body's
fault or if it is somebody's fault that
person well he may be in the room but
he's a little bit
diffuse
uh
frankly we don't understand why the
particles are what they are we don't
understand why there is an electron and
no and uh and no um particle whose name
I slips my mind because nobody's ever
named it because it doesn't exist but
nevertheless why some particles exist
and why other kind of particles don't
exist we largely by and large don't know
we do understand some relationships
between particles if this one and that
one and that one exist then there's got
to be another one to match up with them
in some appropriate way but in the end
of the day um there are many more
parameters many more different types of
particles then there are known
relationships between them which cut
down the size of the problem okay the
the mathematics and the relationships
cut down the size of the problem
somewhat factor of two factor of three
or something like that but there are
hundreds of particles so it is honestly
a
mess uh if you want to understand what
people are hoping for in the next round
of experiments and so forth you have to
understand some of that mess and what
the puzzles are about it so let's begin
let's name the particles
we begin with the most obvious
ones let's make a
table Let's see we need some
columns we can put the name of the
particle over
here I'll put the symbol for the
here I'll put the particle type over
here now what do I mean by type I simply
mean whether it's a firon or Boson
I'll put the electric charge over
here there's another quantity which
characteriz as particles we'll call it
the barion
number I'll tell you what it is as we go
along and there are other part there are
other properties at the moment I'm not
listing them and we'll put the mass over
here all right
the first one of course and I'm not
listing them in any particular order as
it happens I'm I am writing down the
lightest one first the lightest one is
of course the
photon the standard symbol for a photon
is a gamma like for a gamma
ray it has a field associated with it
the gamma particle is the Quantum of a
field in most cases or many cases the
field carries the same symbol as the
part particle itself but for the photon
the field is called a and it's really
the vector potential of the
electromagnetic field you could use
electric or magnetic fields but you can
also use the vector
potential which is another way of
describing the electromagnetic field it
has it's it's a
bon I didn't write down the spin but the
spin is one unit of spin the electric
charge is zero the Baron number whatever
that is is zero and the mass is
zero so that's the first
particle next particle of interest is
the
electron now the electron is a particle
which has an anti-particle it has an
electric charge if it has an electric
charge it must have an anti-particle of
the opposite charge and it is a
convention whether we name the whether
we uh think of the particle
as the electron and the antiparticle as
the positron or whether we think of the
positron as the particle and the
electron is the antiparticle the
relation between them is mutual all
right so when I write the electron I
really mean the electron and positron
and so we could write e here plus
minus standing e minus is the electron
e+ is the positron the field of the
electron is usually
s and maybe you could put a little e
downstairs to indicate that it stands
for the electron it's made up out of
creation and Annihilation operators for
electrons electrons are
Fons it's charge okay it's charge in
what units now well the
standard particle physics or quantum
mechanical unit for electric charge
believe it or not is the electric charge
of an electron it's a good unit to work
in terms of you can go look it up in
kums it's 10 to the minus
what 23 uh 10us 19th KS order yeah it's
some very small charge but
uh but it's not useful to think about it
in
kums all particles in nature have
electric charges which are integer
multiples of the electron charge this
not true of quirks but quirks are not
observable particles all right so the
charge we'll just write as minus one for
the electron and plus one for the
positron right so since we typically
talk think of the electron as a particle
and the positron as the antiparticle
let's just call it minus one and
remember that the positron has the
opposite charge barion number is zero
and it's mass now we have to decide on
units for Mass okay units for Mass are
the same as units for energy eal mc^ s
so we can either describe the mass as a
mass in kilogram or an energy in Jewels
or we can simply invent a new unit which
is more appropriate to microscopic
physics to Atomic physics a in fact the
unit that we use comes originally
historically out of atomic
physics uh it is the unit in which the
ionization energy of an electron in a
hydrogen atom is what 13.5 electron
volts an electron volt is how much
energy you get if you pass an electron
from a across a capacitor plate of one
volt it's a very very small amount of
energy some tiny fraction of a jewel
uh but one electron volt is the standard
unit that came historically out of
atomic physics theory of electrons and
so forth uh it's going to wind up being
too small a unit for us particle physics
energies are larger than Atomic physics
energies but for historical reasons we
have the electron volt is our unit of
energy and the mass of an electron
measured in electron volts is of order a
million electron volts one meev in fact
it's a half an electron volt not exactly
I think it's 0.
51 meev and meev stands for millions of
electron
volts an me will be too small a unit for
many other
purposes uh as I said the particle
physics is a mess and the masses of
particles extend all over the map and so
in try to search for a useful unit
you're always frustrated the useful unit
will always be too small for the next uh
should it be exactly a half no
why no it's exactly 0.
51 no it's
not what's
that Pi
3 pial three pi equals 3 right okay now
we can start
Quantum electrodynamics is the theory of
electrons and photons and we've talked
about it a little bit more than a little
bit and I just we could also write down
over here a table of the various I don't
we'll make it a table we'll just make uh
we'll just draw some pictures the
basic um Elementary process that takes
place in Quantum electrodynamics photons
and
electrons is the emission of a photon by
an electron
electron electron Photon and as I've
showed you several times you can
rearrange the legs of this diagram so
that this could represent not the
emission of a photon but the absorption
of a photon Photon comes in from the
past or whoops
sorry you can even flip the electron
legs around so that it looks like
this electron going backwards in time
what does that mean that really means a
positron emitting a
photon so the basic
um building block for building up
processes and interactions is this
vertex with two electrons electron
positron whatever coming one going in
one going out and a photon coming out of
it or going into it out of that you
build up all of the various processes of
quantum electrodynamics but in
particular the process or the uh the
phenomena that corresponds to the force
between
charges and in the language of particle
exchange it's the photon bouncing back
and forth between charged
particles uh which
um which creates that
Force yet another way to describe what's
going on here is in terms of a lran or a
term in a lran
the lungan describing this process here
describes one electron in one electron
out and one Photon out and so you build
that out of the field
operators one electron
in is p electron it it creates it has
the creation and Annihilation operators
in it an electron out is p Dagger of the
electron and a photon emitted
is the field operator for the photon and
if you plug in all the creation and
Annihilation operators you will find in
here buried in here terms where a photon
is emitted an electron absorbed another
electron emitted and so forth and this
codifies this describes all of the
various basic processes that can happen
in Quantum electr Dynamics now there's a
parameter in the
lran appears
the electric charge of the
electron and that roughly
speaking is associated with the
amplitude for a electron to emit a
photon an electron let's say you hit the
electron or whatever the electron plows
into the side of a x-ray machine what's
the probability that a photon will be
emitted well the amplitude is the
electric charge and the probability is
proportional to for the square of the
electric charge so all of this
here is a way of
describing all of these basic processes
and when they're combined together they
produce forces they produce processes
where photons are emitted the whole
world of quantum electrodynamics flows
out of this basically one expression
here we won't try to go through that
again
now
uh but let's start adding a little bit
to our particle
list the next particles of Interest
these are of course familiar to you I'm
sure right now if this were 1960 when I
when I well I
was 1962 when I went to graduate school
probably the next particles I might
write down would be protons and
neutrons uh protons and neutrons are now
subsumed by
quirks it is is widely believed that in
some sense protons and neutrons are
composits of quirks although we will
come remind me to come back to this
issue of the difference or what what it
means to be composite versus Elementary
it's a very interesting story but
naively quirks are smaller than protons
and
neutrons and so protons and neutrons
which are big fat Globs are made up out
of quarks okay so next thing are quirks
there's a lot of quirks we won't even
get to to all of them tonight or the
whole set of distinctions between them I
don't think we will
but there's more than one type of
Quirk there are six types of quirks six
distinct particles all of which are very
similar to each other in some respects
very different from each other in
different other respects so let's list
them
there are they go in they have names all
right well why are they called what they
are they called what they are just uh
historically randomly people assigned
silly names to them and there's no logic
to what they're called no logic at all
there's first of all the upk and that's
called U the symbol is U well let's see
we should write there were quirks here
quirks
and I suppose the symbol for quarks is
Q all quarks are Fons we'll write down
their charge later they have all barion
number of
13 now why 1/3 well the reason is very
simple the barion number is basically
the counting of the number of protons
and
neutrons each proton is counted as
having one unit of barion number each
Neutron is car counted as having one
unit of Baron is just a word for protons
and neutrons and and a and a somewhat
generalization of protons and
neutrons um nucleon is a word for for
protons and neutrons there are other
particles which will come to which are
very similar to to protons and neutrons
they're also called
Barons uh the prefix Barry I think means
heavy
um and Barons we called Barons because
they're a lot heavier than
electrons but counting up the number of
protons and neutrons what do you call
the number of protons plus neutrons in
an
atom the atomic weight yeah I always the
atomic weight yeah the atomic weight uh
is
equal approximately equal to the total
number of protons and
neutrons and the total number of protons
and neutrons in nuclear physics never
changes protons can turn into neutrons
neutrons can turn into protons plus
other things
uh but uh the number of protons plus
neutrons never changes and isop H you
have isotopes you do have isotopes but
still the number of protons plus
neutrons doesn't
change um number of protons can change
how how can a number of protons change
no no I'm just saying that different
isotopes have different numbers of
neutrons oh yeah indeed they do but uh
are there processes where the number of
protons and neutrons change protons not
plus neutrons but protons Andor neutrons
change beta Decay radioactivity in
radioactivity one form of radioactivity
a neutron decays into a proton plus an
electron and an anti-
neutrino okay so in that process the
number of protons changes by one the
number of neutrons changes by one but
the number of protons plus neutrons
doesn't
change uh there's a generalization of
that in all of nuclear physics and
particle physics there's a certain
quantity which for ordinary Nuclear
Physics is just the number of protons
plus
neutrons and that number is sometimes
called the barion
number we'll have to generalize it a
little bit beyond protons and neutrons
it's a barion number and it could have
been defined to be two for the proton or
seven for the proton or Pi for the
proton but whatever it is it has to be
defined as twice as much for two protons
three times as much much for three
protons so it's a convention that you
say the barion number of the proton is
one incidentally what's the baron number
of the
antiproton minus one minus
one proton has bar on number plus one
anti-proton barion number minus one
neutron barion number one anti- neutron
barion number minus one but clearly
there's an element of convention in
exactly what you call
them uh but once it was fixed that the
barion number of a proton was one then
the barion number of a quark was a third
because three quarks make a proton okay
so it's just a historical glitch that
the bar on number of the most
fundamental thing in nuclear physics is
1/3 and not one what about an antiquark
there are
antiquarks variant number is minus A3
right so I won't write that down
separately the number of quartes is
conserved number of quarks minus the
number of antiquarks is conserved now
whether or not that is an absolute
conservation
law it is not believed to be an absolute
conservation law what do I mean by
absolute conservation law can a proton
disappear it can completely disappear it
energy has to go
someplace are there processes in nature
where a proton might disappear and
become something that is n either a
proton or a neutron or anything else
that you would call a barion for example
without violating charge conservation a
proton could become a positron and a
photon so a proton could Decay into a
positron and a photon does it well you
can wait a if you have a single proton
and you sit there and wait you will wait
a long long time before that proton
decays it's halflife
to Decay that way is at least 10 to the
33 or 10 to the 34
years so this is not something that
happens very
regularly does it happen at all the
thinking is yes it does but this is one
of the very very interesting questions
of particle physics of whether the
proton can Decay and when you say can it
decay you mean Decay into something that
does not carry a Barrion
number uh
and it is widely believed that the
answer is yes but has never been
demonstrated incidentally how do you how
do you waigh around for 10 to the 34
years for a proton to Decay you get 10
to the 34 protons and you wait around
for one of them and you to see
one now 10^ the 34 protons is a lot of
protons if you have protons and anons no
that that's not that that that's zero
Barrion number because goes to zero
Baron number
a proton has barion number one a
anti-proton has Baron number minus one
so that's not a barion we call them
barion violating processes processes in
which the barion number is not conserved
nobody has ever witnessed such a uh
process in the laboratory or any place
else uh can they happen there does not
seem to be any reason why they cannot
happen built into the mathematics of
what we know so we leave this as an open
question but empirically and at least to
a very very high Precision barion number
is conserved and quirks by definition
have 1/3 of a unit 1/3 of a unit as I
said minus a third for anti quarks but
in order to fill in the rest of this in
particular electric charge and mass we
have to label which kind of Quark we're
talking about and there are lots of
different kinds of quirks so let's put
in the list of different kinds of quirks
this is not new particles which are not
quirks this is just a subheading here
quarks and then things underneath there
are up quirks down quirks why are they
up and down they're not up and down
there's nothing up and down about them
uh
H what directions up and down up and
down means in the earth's gravitational
field there's nothing uppy or downy
about
them right then it gets worse there are
strange quarks which are No Stranger
Than non- strange
quarks it gets more and silly there are
charm
quirks which are Charming I suppose I
don't know and then there are now this
is if you don't you know if if you're um
if you're squeamish or you know very
they bottom quirks bottom
quirks bottom quirks and then top quirks
and the symbols are of course exactly
the same I I just didn't feel like
writing the words up down strange charm
bottom top what there Beauty and Truth
same as bottom and top I got a little
pretentious Beauty and truth so bottom
and top strange and
charm how and under what circumstances
these things were named is um
not not
interesting I don't know I do know but
never mind they're all fans okay the
symbols are just what I wrote here
they're all what's the field
symb uh some sometimes Q sometimes s
q sometimes capital
Q sometimes depending if you're talking
about the individual types of them
you'll just use u d s c b or t use the
same names for the fields as you use for
the particles
uh and there's no completely coherent
convention that everybody sticks to all
right they're all firion the whole lot
of them are Fons as I said but now comes
the charges so it's useful to divide
them into groups of
two these groups of
two are sort of repetitions of each
other
this group of two in many ways is
isomorphic not exactly to this group of
two which is the same as not the same
but which follows the same pattern the
pattern of these two is similar to the
pattern of these two is similar oh I got
them upside down excuse me wait if I
want to keep the
pattern let me see um I think I want to
put down
up down up strange down up strange charm
bottom top yeah
uh all right so the down up system is
very similar to The Strange charm system
is very similar to the bottom top system
so let's write down what the electric
charges are and you can see them you can
see this
similarity the down up system has charge
minus
A3 and
2/3 that's the first example of
particles in nature which have charges
which are not integer multiples of the
electric charge of the
electron okay however quirks by
themselves do not exist freely in nature
they're always bound into other
structures protons neutrons and so forth
and those particles do have integer
charges okay the strange and the charm
exactly the same thing minus A3 and
2/3 bottom and top exactly the sameus A3
and 2/3 can that be
read they're just repetitions of the
same thing what about the anti particles
if I were to list the anti particles
over here they would just have exactly
the same charges as the particles except
opposite
sign so this
is simply replication for some reason
that nobody understands nobody even has
any idea why nature replicated itself
this way are they still all on
number yeah they're all burying on
number one3 right okay and then the
masses the masses are not similar to
each
other the masses wildly
vary I'm going to put down estimates for
them because uh the precise value well
there are precise values of the masses
but you can go look them up on Google or
wherever you want uh the down
Quark is about 10
me so it's 50 times heavier than the
electron a lot lighter than the proton
incidentally what's the proton
Mass 1800 18 about 1,00 times the
electron mass in other words about 940
me this is a lot lighter than a proton
the up Quark about 5 me less than the
uh than the down quark and protons are
made only out of up quarks and down
quirks so it doesn't look like there's
nearly enough mass in
quirks to uh to be the mass of a proton
or Neutron okay we'll come back to that
point is of course there's more in a
proton than just a uh it's
quirks okay strange in charm strange is
roughly order of magnitude 100
m that's
strange and charm is little over about a
th000
meev now notice that the down Quark is
heavier than the up Quark but the
strange Quark which is analogous to the
down Quark is lighter than the charm
Quirk so there's some pattern of
inversion here of the
masses again nobody understands at all
why that's
true yeah charm is about a, 12 a little
more than
that
sorry 100 missed a zero decimal
creep okay 1,000 me and the botom cork
is about 5,000 oh this is called a
gev giga electron
volt the bottom Quirk see we keep
changing
units that's about 5
gev and the top Quirk is about 170
gev so how much heavier is the top Quark
than the up
Quirk can any anybody do that
calculation how much 30,000 a lot a lot
all right so on the one hand these
particles are extremely similar to each
other they do the same things they have
the same properties and yet they have
masses which wander all over the map
does anybody understand why no are there
any ideas yes do any of them work no
we don't even have a clue about why
there's we first of all we don't even
understand of course why there's even
one of
them one family these are called
families why is there one family well we
don't know but for sure if there wasn't
one family we wouldn't be here because
there would be no protons and neutrons
but given that there's this one family
of up quirks and down quirks why are
there strange quarks and charm quarks or
top quarks and bottom quarks nobody has
a
clue stupid question question when these
quirks were
found the story goes that they were
looking in a certain place because the
math said the mass should be a certain
amount something this in other words
they said they said that they they went
through the calculations and they knew
that this is where it was going to be
that it was going to be somewhere around
so many G that they were going to find
top in
particular yeah they predicted that it
would be there before they went and
looked for it yeah but not on the basis
of you know abstract Theory but on the
basis of uh of you know how the top cork
would affect the work its way into uh
other particles properties I was just
saying because you just said that the
numbers and nobody knows why and they're
all over the ballpark but yet they seem
to know that that's where they wanted to
look for it yeah but not not because
um not because there was any basic
underlying reason why the top Quirk had
that
mass what you could do is you could say
supposing the top quk had a certain mass
and then calculate various Fineman
diagrams involving the top quk in
various
ways Fineman diagrams involving ordinary
particles not the top Quark but which
had top quarks running around in the
interior of
diagrams okay you calculate those
diagrams those diagrams have an effect
on processes involving other particles
that you know very well and then you say
how what does the mass of this top cork
have to be in order that it uh does the
right thing uh for these other particles
right so it was not in any sense a deep
understanding of why the mass of the top
cork was what it was it was simply an
observation that you needed that
particular value the top cork mass in
order that it uh that it be consistent
with
yeah so you you can't observe a cork but
you can predict how it will disappear
what will happen if there is time of
showers and directions ener of particles
will
be go ahead you're asking you're saying
um to say that you can't detect the
Quark becomes to a certain extent a
matter of
definition um what it means to detect a
quirk you can certainly detect evidence
of quarks what you can't do is create an
isolated
Quark in isolation from other things and
then examine it uh but we'll come we're
going to come to the question you I
think you're probably remarking about
Jets produced well I don't know what
you're talking yeah yeah we can talk
about Jets come let's come back to it uh
after we've after we talk more
about there the fact that some books
have tce charged absolute values other
is that from the theory or is that just
a bookkeeping semi Theory yeah to some
extent that that that is
understood I'm not going to explain it
now but uh now I'm telling you the facts
uh we can talk about how much of this is
explained and how much of it how much of
the pattern is the right question is how
much of this pattern is required for
theoretical mathematical
consistency but we haven't gotten there
yet some of this pattern is required
yeah some of this pattern is required
but not much of it very little of it is
required by mathematical
consistency question no is the relative
abundance of the six kinds of
qus abundance in where but what do you
mean by relative
abundance you mean in the world in the
universe
yeah there are very there are neutrons
are unstable they Decay protons are
stable they exist in Intergalactic space
and everything
else they're all oh yeah the only thing
that has any appreciable abundance all
the all right first of all the only
quirks which have any degree of
stability are ups and Bounds the rest of
these Decay to these so real the real
abundance of real particles in the
universe are all ups and downs Okay now
what's the relative abundance of ups and
downs that's determined by how many
quarks of each type there are in a
proton there are no neutrons oh sorry of
course there are neutrons there are
neutrons and atoms uh in the nuclei
so you have to know the relative
abundance of protons and neutrons to uh
to know the the relative abundance of
but that's all it is relative abundance
of protons and
neutrons okay so what do we know what is
a proton and what is a neutron in this
language and let's come over here a
proton is three quarks and a neutron is
three
quarks now as I said I'm now in the
business of telling you facts about
these particles not at this point trying
to understand why these are the
facts we can't do everything at
once a
neutron is two down quarks and an up
Quark let's just check that an up Quark
has charge
2/3 and a down Quirk has charged minus
A3 so 2/3 minus a thir minus another
third this is electrically neutral
charge equals zero that's good neutron
has charge zero
proton proton is exactly the same as a
neutron except with an interchange of up
quirks and down
quirks two up quirks and a down
Quark
okay now
up quirks and down quirks are a lot
alike except for their electric charge
the electric charge has to do with the
interaction with
photons let's forget photons let's
forget about the existence of photons
for the moment and just talk about
quirks and the other particles uh which
are important inside the nucleus and so
forth then it would almost seem that a
neutron and a proton are the same thing
except for an interchange of the up
label and the down label you might then
surmise that they are that they
properties are almost exact or are
exactly the same if for some reason the
electric charge is unimportant in other
words supposing we don't have to worry
about the interaction with photons just
forget photons then it would seem that
protons and neutrons should be identical
cuz what's the difference you just
replaced up quirks by down quirks but
it's not quite true true because up
quirks and down quirks don't have
exactly the same mass right they don't
have exactly the same mass now 10 meev
by comparison with the mass of a proton
is small it's almost
negligible it is very small and it's
almost negligible in nuclear physics or
in uh in particle physics and so to a to
some Precision to the extent that you
can ignore the masses of the quirk which
are after all smaller by far than the
masses of protons and neutrons neutrons
and protons are a good deal alike right
the only difference is the slight
difference in Mass between the up quirks
and the down quirks which one is going
to be heavier the nutron or the proton
and of course it's going to be the one
with more down quirks because down
quirks are a bit heavier than up
quirks down quarks are a bit heavier
than up quarks and so it's likely that
the neutron is heavier than the prot and
it is okay Neutron is a little bit
heavier than the
proton and it's largely attributed to
the um uh to the fact that the neutron
has more down quirks now that's not all
there is to the difference between
protons and
neutrons if the down quirks and the up
quirks had exactly the same mass but you
accounted for electromagnetism in other
words the photon you said okay the
photon is not completely unimportant
then which would be
heavier the proton or the
neutron
why yes because it has some
electrostatic self energy because it's
charged okay so the proton would be a
little bit heavier because of the
electric the self energy of the
electromagnetic field the electric field
one would expect the proton to be a
little bit heavier in fact the neutron
is a little bit heavier
uh and the reason is because the down
Quirk is a little bit heavier than the
up
Quirk okay but other than that you going
to give us the masses of which neutrons
and
proton yeah um Neutron is about what 938
uh me and proton is about 939 me
or was about 1.4 me uh me difference
between
them something like about 1.4 M
difference between them there's enough
energy between them there's enough
energy separating them that the neutron
can afford a little bit of energy to
when it decays into a um a proton plus
an electron plus a nutrino there a
little bit of excess energy in the
nutrino which allows it to
Decay and what allows it in particular
to Decay with an electron to an electron
okay so that's the very very rough story
of protons and neutrons we'll come back
to it but now there are also these
strange quarks let's forget Charmed
quarks for a moment there's an
interesting question can you replace now
notice that in every respect the down
quirks and the strange quirks are
similar to each other except for the
fact that the mass is different so you
might ask ask can you
construct an analog of the proton and
neutron where you pull out a down quark
and replace it by a strange Quark or
perhaps two strange quarks pull out a
down quark and replace it by a strange
Quark the answer is yes of course you
can because in every respect the up
quirks and the down quirks are the same
it's sort of almost like an isotope you
pull out a proton and put it in a
neutron and it sort of sticks together
sort of the same way but it's even
better here uh so you can construct
another kind of
analog these are called strange Barons
strange Barons I forget their names
lambdas and Si they've got all kinds of
names and you know it's been so long
since I uh since I worked on these
things that I can't even remember their
names they have symbols like this
associated with them like this and
lambdas I don't remember which one is
which not important but for example you
can
create I don't know what its name is uh
pull out a down Quirk and create a
strange and a down and an up what's the
mass of this one over here sorry not the
mess what is the charge of this one well
it's exactly the same as a neutron
because you pulled out a down and put in
an S and the S and the down have the
same
charge all right so this is also
electrically neutral
but it has a strange Quark in it and
it's called a strange barion okay
they're not stable they can Decay we're
going to discuss the the Decay processes
later but they're not completely stable
so they evaporate then this one will
turn into that one but yes they do exist
likewise you can put in two strange
quarks and an up Quark what is the
charge of that one same thing charge
neutral again and likewise uh like wise
for the proton you can replace it by up
up and strange so there are all these
strange
Barons when they when when those Decay
what what kind of uh products do you
have what kind of what products do you
have oh protons and
neutrons only protons and neutrons uh
yeah well no no you get the some uh pons
and other things
like electron and other things of course
you can't just get get and you you also
only substituted Stranges for Downs um
yeah and not UPS
or no you can't no this well
um the rules of what you can exchange
are a little bit complicated but at the
moment you can always exchange one for a
similar one of the same charge all right
now you can
also oh incidentally these strange
particles are a little bit heavier than
the protons and neutrons because of this
extra 90 me of well no yeah an extra 90
me 90 M isn't much right so they're
somewhat heavier than uh the ordinary
protons and neutrons but in every
respect they're similar the main
difference of importance is because
they're heavier they can Decay to the
protons and neutrons and uh and so they
they're not found in the universe in any
abundance all of those that you put up
there so far can be constructed with
antiks also oh yes yeah you you have to
take every particle and replace it by
its anti- particle then it becomes the
anti- neutron the anti-proton and the
anti- mark excuse me uh you call these
strange bar strange stress is just
another word for saying they have a
strange
quk but but but if you but if you put a
bottom quk in okay then they become
bottom they're bottom Barons then they
bottom Barons strange Barons is you put
an yeah yeah yeah strange are they
strange well I don't know I
mean they were called strange because
you know people became familiar with
protons and neutrons by the
1950s and then when they discover these
other things oh that's strange and uh
unexpected things yeah where's where's
the missing M from the proton and
neutron missing Mass what do you mean
the Oh you mean if you just added up the
mass of the
quirks right yeah that's right there's a
lot missing so there must be something
else in the proton and
neutron no no they're gluons yeah no no
no uh no attempt here to be
dramatic uh but the gluons don't carry
any interesting charge barion number uh
do they carry Mass well they carry
energy so back to what you were saying
there it's binding energy it's it's it's
a form of binding energy yeah that's
right it's binding
energy energies don't add not
relativistically I mean well masses
don't add the mass of an object is not
necessarily the mass of its
constituents well it's what you were
saying about the prevalance bond type
thing right here you're using a language
of particles here to describe these
composite particles it seems more
complicated if use the word language of
fields like how would you combine a down
field and up field it seems like you
would combine everywhere not be a
particle a field
uh you want to know whether you can
construct a field describing a proton uh
yeah you're using down and up as if
they're particles but if you think as
Fields then they're everywhere and modes
of the field are combining to form these
composite particles well in thinking
yeah I mean in thinking about this
particular aspect of things it's much
easier to think about uh about particles
than
Fields is we could think about it in
terms of fields but it's much
harder and question about the binding
energies
yeah so if you if this difference
between the quart energies and the the
proton energy or binding
energy um that's a big positive energy
no not an integer it's not an integer no
it's big positive energy energy Oh I
thought you said integer yeah and
usually when you think of things being B
usually negative right right not true
here well yeah I mean we we'll come to
it but uh yeah sure
um uh yes yes let's let's yes there is
yes there is but not
yet let's talk first about mesons
mesons are simply Quark anti- Quark now
why you know you could raise a question
why do three quarks bind together to
form something why don't two quarks bind
together to form something okay in the
early days of quirkology this was a
complete mystery why quirks always you
could say oh it's in order to make the
charge an integer multiple of the
electron well that's a stupid answer and
uh turn out not to be that stupid but at
this at this stage it's a stupid answer
um but yet that is the pattern that is
the pattern that they combine together
in forms in which This Is Not the Only
Rule but this is one of the rules of
nature we do understand it and we do
understand where it comes from but a
rule a rule of thumb at the present time
is the way things bind they always bind
into combinations which have integer
multiple of the electron charge
okay so you can take that as a working
rule uh temporarily until we have a
deeper understanding of
it all right mesons are
also particles composite particles which
also have the property that their charge
is integer
multiple of the electron charge but they
have zero barion number they do not have
barion number which means that they must
be made they're quk they're combinations
of quirks they must be made of quirks
and
antiquarks in fact they
are quirks a quark and an anti-
Quark they're a quark and an antiquark
and so let's uh let's write down there
are first of all the ones that you can
make only out of ups and down quarks ups
and down quarks are special not in any
deep sense but they're special because
they're much lighter than the other
particles they don't Decay or they don't
Decay as rapidly if they do Decay um
they're abundant in nature and more than
that it doesn't take any energy in a it
doesn't take much energy in collisions
to make them so of course they were the
first particles to be discovered things
made up of only up quarks and down
quarks the up quarks and down quarks are
pretty light and the mesons are
typically pretty light they're an upcar
and down and an anti or a quk and an
anti- quark and then you can start
thinking about the different
combinations there's an up bar quark and
a down Quark there's a down an up quark
and a down bar
Quark there's an up bar and an up quark
and there's a down bar and a down
quk I think I got them all
have the opposite spin any have the
opposite spin no you can't do that don't
they have to don't they have to be the
opposite kind because it's 1/3 and 2/3
so it's got to be
no okay let's let's work out what their
electric charges are the electric charge
of an upcar is minus 2/3 and this one is
minus 1/3 this has
charge minus one right
minus A3 minus
2/3 that's fine charge minus one is like
a like an electron you're all right what
about this one this is the anti-particle
of
this this one's not this one is just the
anti particle of this I was oh yes right
right this one is the anti these two are
antiparticles of each other because they
are related by changing particles into
antiparticles down bar into down up bar
into up and this has charge +
one so these are antiparticles of each
other up bar up that's electrically
neutral
obviously and charge equals zero now in
fact neither one of these two by
themselves correspond to distinct
particles remember we're doing quantum
mechanics each one of these
States can be thought of as a Quantum
State think of it as a Quantum State the
quantum State consisting of an anti-up
quark and an up Quark the quantum State
consisting of an anti- down quark and a
down
Quark one of the things you can do in
quantum mechanics is to superpose States
if you have States you can add them you
can superpose them superposing them
means making combinations that have a
probab ability for being either this one
or this
one right there are two combinations of
these two and I'll tell you tell you
what they are they are up bar
up plus down bar
down and what would I put in front of it
to make it have total probability
one 1/ < TK of
two this is a Quantum state and this is
another this is the orthogonal Quantum
State up bar up minus down bar
down you know what this is this is an
entangled pair of quirks not entangled
through their spin but entangled through
their upness or
down if you thought of upness and down
as like being similar analogous to the
spin direction of a particle up or down
and that's where this terminology came
from then these would be two entangled
States entangled not through their spin
but through their isospin through their
upness and down we haven't used the word
isospin maybe I'll I'll tell you what it
means but not right
now uh it is just this analogy between
the spin directions in the upness or
down this quantum number these two
things individually are well-defined
particles this one over
here goes together with these
two and they are called the
pons they go
together for a good reason for a good
mathematical reason but they go together
do I have the right one on yeah they go
together because their mass is very
close to each other it is believed they
would be exactly the same mass if the up
Quirk and down Quark had the same exact
Mass if they were if the masses were the
same uh all three of these are virtually
indistinguishable except for a small
difference in their mass and they have
different charges 0 + one and minus one
and this is called the pon multiplet
pi plus minus and zero three independent
kinds of particles called
pons and as I said and we can discuss
why nature chose these particular
combinations uh to be analogous to each
other but now I'm telling you facts and
not the not mathematics and the other
combination is simply this one over
here and this is called the Ada
the so there's the pi plus the four
states here really Define the three pons
pi plus minus and zero and the
adeson the adeson is similar to a Pion
in many ways but it's heavier why is it
heavier that is a complicated story it's
not an elementary story it's a
complicated story maybe we will come to
it maybe we won't but as a matter of
fact it's Mass okay what are the masses
of the pons the masses of the pons are
about 140
me the mass of a Pion mass of Pion M Pi
is
about 140
me so in other words it's not too
different
from question yeah it's about 140 meev
so it's somewhere is in this range
here not this heavy and the mass of the
Ada is about three times heavier or
something like that the mass of the Ada
is about 500
me I don't remember the precise number
but that's about
right why that is why the Ada sticks out
as being different was a puzzle for a
long time it's a and not obvious not
obvious even today it's a rather ma
abstract mathematic
iCal uh fact but it is it is
understood isn't it also true there Ro
long half life not very long compared to
most of them they're like numers of
orders of magnitude
different uh they don't Decay by strong
interactions they Decay by weak and
electromagnetic interactions so they're
longer lived than uh than many of these
uh these other particles yes that is
true
right they are long
liveed okay that those are the mesons
did you give a name to the up bar down
down
bar yeah those are no they don't have
names by themselves the're linear
combination which are the sum and
differences of them have definite
names oh yes is that similar
to is that something like the nutral
isolations
well in the sense that it's related to
Super Quantum superpositions of States
yes but it's got more to do with spin
combinations of two halfs spin
particles uh there are two ways that you
can entangle well we'll come to it next
time the last thing I simply want to
tell you is that you can make strange
mesons you can take any de quar and
replace it by a strange
Quark strange bar quark and so forth
that makes new mesons which are called
strange mesons or what's the other name
for
them k
mesons k mesons are mesons containing a
strange or an anti-st strange Quark
replacing a down
Quirk okay there are four of
them upar
strange uh up strange bar down bar
strange down strange
bar these two have charge
zero charge
zero and these have charge + one and
minus one these two are called the
charged K mesons these two are called
the neutral change the the neutral K
mesons so there are three kinds of pons
one kind of ADA and four kinds of how
many does that make all together let's
see
uh three
pons four K mesons and an ADA yeah yeah
yeah there's more there's more there's
more oh did we leave something
out
um yeah we left out one we left out we
left out some uh we yeah we left out
SARS
huh yeah
nine
right right nine nine Al together the
reason it's nine is simple there are
three kinds of quirks three kinds of
antiquarks 3 * 3 is
nine
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu